Guide to the Elmer Louis Kayser papers, 1824-1985 MS0245.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Professional papers, 1921-1973; MS0245 Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet (Box 29, Box 28, Box 27, Box 26, Box 30)
  - Mt. Vernon Seminary, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Committee, St. Elizabeth Hospital, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - American Association of Collegiate Registrars, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - American Association of University Professors, undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Committees: American Association of University Professors, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Committees: American Association of University Professors, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Papers related to professional membership in American Bar Association, undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Papers related to professional membership in American Bar Association, undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Professional Association Membership: American Historical Association, undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Professional Association Memberships: American Historical Association (1), 1973 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Professional Association Memberships: American Historical Association (2), 1973 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Professional Association Memberships: American Historical Association (3), 1973 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - American Historical Association, 1944-1945 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - American Historical Association (Kayser Chairman of Publicity), 1944-1945 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - American Historical Association, undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - American Historical Association: Treasurer Report, 1957-1958 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Professional Association Memberships: American Historical Association (4), 1973 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Professional Association Memberships: Association of History Teachers, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Professional Association Memberships: Association of History Teachers of the Middle States and Maryland, undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Professional Association Memberships American Oriental Society, undated (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Professional Association Memberships: The American Peace Society, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Professional Association Memberships Association of Urban Universities, undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Professional Association Memberships Columbia Historical Society, undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Committees: IPMA Awards Committee (International Personnel Management Association), undated (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Professional Association Memberships: Governing Board National Cathedral School, 1943-1957 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Institute of Central-Eastern European Affairs, Hofstra College, Hempstead, Long Island, 1945 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Life Officers Investment Seminar, The American Life Convention, 1946 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - National Association Postal Supervisors, undated (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - National Capital Sesquicentennial, 1950-1951 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - National Capital Sesquicentennial, 1949-1950 (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - National Defense Health Clinics, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Navy Advisory Committee, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Navy Advisory Committee, undated (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - SECNAV (Advisory Committee on Naval History), 1958 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - SECNAV (Advisory Committee on Naval History), 1958 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Committees: Nurse's Examining Board Committee, Chair, 1934-1937 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Strategic Intelligence School (Elements of National Power-Lecture Series), undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission/Office of Care Development, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Turner Diplomatic School, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Travel: President's Highway Safety Conference, 1948 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Travel: Switzerland, 1921 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Travel: United Nations General Assembly, 1953 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - War Department, undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - WMAL Radio Broadcast, undated (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - WTOP Radio Broadcast, undated (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - TOP radio Broadcasts, "Today in History", undated (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - WTOP radio Broadcasts, "Today in History", undated (Box 28, Folder 17)
  - WTOP radio Broadcasts, "Today in History", undated (Box 28, Folder 18)
  - WTOP radio Broadcasts, "Today in History", undated (Box 28, Folder 19)
  - WTOP radio Broadcasts, "Today in History", undated (Box 28, Folder 20)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - TOP Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - WDC Radio Broadcasts, undated (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Radio Broadcast: Evening Star Newspaper, undated (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - WMAL Radio Broadcast, undated (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - WJSU Radio Broadcast, undated (Box 30, Folder 10)
- Personal papers, 1824-1985; MS0245 Series 3; 6 Linear feet (Box 40, Box 41, Box 38, Box 39, Box 42, Box 32, Box 33, Box 31, Box 36, Box 37, Box 34, Box 35)
  This series contains correspondence, books, educational records, financial documents, invitations, photographs, artifacts, and a video tape. The material covers the years 1824-1967. These materials relate to Elmer Kayer's life outside of GW including his time with the Cosmos Club and National Press Club, his bank statements and income tax returns, family correspondence, military service, student records, a promissory note signed by Luther Rice, and a video tape of Kayser discussing the history of the University.
  - Autobiographies, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Biography, undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Career Move: University of Maine, 1932 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Charity activities, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Charity activities, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Church related activities, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Church related activities, undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Church Related Activities: Bible Talks, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Activities in St. Albans Parish, undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Activities in St. Albans Parish, undated (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Civic Associations Cosmos Club, 1955-56 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Civic Associations: Cosmos Club, undated (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Civic Associations: Cosmos Club, Kayser resignation, undated (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Civic Associations: National Press Club, undated (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Summons for Jury Duty, 1957 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Civil Service Examination, 1917 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Family Correspondence, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Family Correspondence: J.W.H. War Letters, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Family Correspondence: T.B.L. War Letters, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Family Correspondence, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Christmas Greetings, undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Ludlow Papers, undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Diocese of Washington: Committee on College Work, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Diocesan Committee, undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Hans Baron, undated (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Louis Ludlow, undated (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: E.L. Kayser - Waldo Girdner - Meador Wright Correspondence, undated (Box 34, Folder 15)
  - Education at Columbia University, undated (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Education at Columbia University, undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Education at Columbia University, undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Education at George Washington University, undated (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Education at George Washington University, undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Education at George Washington University, undated (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Education: American University, undated (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Education: John Hopkins University, undated (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Education: Yale University, undated (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records: Income Tax Documents, 1967 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Letters of Reference, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Education: Columbia University - Lynn Thorndike Lecture Notes, undated (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Education at Columbia University, undated (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Education at Columbia University, undated (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Conference on the Limitation of Armament, undated (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Financial Records: Bank Statements, 1966 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records: Bank Statements, 1965 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Financial Records: Income Tax Receipts, 1966 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Financial Records: Donations, 1966 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records: Bank Statements, The National Bank of Washington, 1967 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records: Bank Statememnts, 1967 (Box 38, Folder 10)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 38, Folder 11)
  - Financial Records: Income Tax, 1948-1951 (Box 38, Folder 12)
  - Invitations to Speak, 1938-1939 (Box 38, Folder 13)
  - Invitations to Speak, 1937-1939 (Box 38, Folder 14)
  - Invitations to Speak, 1935-1937 (Box 38, Folder 15)
  - Invitations to Speak L. Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Invitations to Speak, undated (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Invitations to Speak: American Institute of Banking, undated (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Invitations to Speak: St. Andrews Association, undated (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Invitations to Speak, undated (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Invitations to Speak, undated (Box 39, Folder 10)
  - Invitations to Speak, undated (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 12)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 39, Folder 13)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Medical Records, undated (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Medical Records: MLK's illness, 1946 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Medical Records, undated (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Medical Records, undated (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Medical Records, 1966 (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Military Service, undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Public Schools: District of Columbia, undated (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Public Schools, undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - ELK's student record and memorabilia - Columbia, undated (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Education: Memorabilia, undated (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Student Records And Memorabilia from education years, undated (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Student Records And Memorabilia from education years, undated (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Student Records And Memorabilia from education years, undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - Student records and memorabilia: History 270, The Expansion of the European Civilization (Sheperd), undated (Box 41, Folder 10)
  - Student records and memorabilia World Community (Shotwell), undated (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - Student records and memorabilia Seminar Notes, undated (Box 41, Folder 12)
  - Student records and memorabilia; English Constitution (Schuyler), undated (Box 41, Folder 13)
  - Student records and memorabilia: A History of the Neutrality of Belgium, Switzerland and Luxemburg - International Law, undated (Box 41, Folder 14)
  - Education: Memorabilia, undated (Box 41, Folder 15)
  - Social Events, undated (Box 41, Folder 16)
  - Biographical Data (Printed), undated (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Realia: Print, Seal of Columbian College (framed), 1860 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Realia; Promisory Note $500-Luther Rice (framed), 05/24/1824 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Video Tape: Elmer Kayser, GWU Historian speaking about the early days of this university on GW TV, 1985 -circa (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - List of Books received with the manuscript collection, transferred to Gift Acquisition Department, undated (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Platform scene, Centennial Convocation, George Washington University, 1921 February 22; Series 3 (Map-folder 1)
    General
    This is a panorama. In the folder with the image is a detailed list identifying people in the image
  - George Washington University Baccalaureate Sermon, Peace Cross, Cathedral Closure, 1921 June 5; Series 3 (Map-folder 2)
    This is a panorama
  - 1918 Camp Zachary Taylor 45th Tr. Battery, 1918 November 26; Series 3 (Map-folder 3)
    This is a panorama. Writen on image "45th Tr. Battery F.A.C.O. T.S. 1st Lieut. V.M. Vanderwaal Comdg. Nov. 26th. 1918 Camp Zachary Taylor, Louisville, KY."
- Correspondence, writtings, and records, 1826-2002; MS0245 Series 4; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 43)
  This series contains correspondence, memorandums, envelopes, speeches, press releases, programs, awards, speeches, publications, and articles written by Kayser. They range in date from 1826 to 1982. The materials concern requestes for information about William Staughton and Staughton's paintings by Peale to Kayser and John Russell Mason by Staughton's family. The materials also concern biographical information about Kayser.
  - History of GW 1819-1850, undated (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Kayser, Elmer Louis, 06/04/1967-05/2002 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Kayser, Elmer Louis -- Articles for GW Magazine, 1966-04/25/1972 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Kayser, Elmer Louis -- Obituaries/Eulogies, 04/28/1985-04/29/1985 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Kayser, Elmer Louis -- Professorship in History, 05/04/1983-1983 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Kayser, Elmer Louis -- Publications, 1970-1973 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Kayser, Elmer Louis -- Speeches, 11/03/1949-11/12/1975 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - University Historian, Office of - Kayser, Elmer Louis, 08/16/1963-02/12/1982 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - University Historian, Office of - Staughton, William - Correspondence with Hayden Re: Staughton, 05/19/1964-03/08/1965 (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - University Historian, Office of - Staughton, William - Family, 1917-11/05/1977 (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - University Historian, Office of - Staughton, William Family - Geneology, 12/12/1958-09/10/1975 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - University Historian, Office of - Staughton, William List of Correspondence, 1972 (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - University Historian, Office of - Staughton, William - Memoir of the Rev. William Staughton, D.D. (Lynd, Rev. Samuel W., son-in-law of Staughton, the Author), 02/02/1947-01/28/1974 (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - University Historian, Office of - Staughton, William - Portraits--Supporting Documents, 08/12/1826-08/16/1971 (Box 43, Folder 14)